<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative plainly shewing, that the priests of England are as truely Antichrist (who got up since the dayes of the Apostles) as the pope and his clergie denying Christ to be both a king, a priest, and a prophet; : with a serious warning to the Parliament not to uphold and maintain them by a law, under any pretence whatsoever ... / By one who ... hath escaped the snares of sin and deceit, and bin [sic] brought ... into His pure fear, known by the name of John Chandler.</title>
            <author>Chandler, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1927B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789214</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2637:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative plainly shewing, that the priests of England are as truely Antichrist (who got up since the dayes of the Apostles) as the pope and his clergie denying Christ to be both a king, a priest, and a prophet; : with a serious warning to the Parliament not to uphold and maintain them by a law, under any pretence whatsoever ... / By one who ... hath escaped the snares of sin and deceit, and bin [sic] brought ... into His pure fear, known by the name of John Chandler.</title>
                  <author>Chandler, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172526:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE PLAINEY SHEWING, That the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> are as truely Antichriſt (who got up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles) as the Pope and His Clergie: Denying Chriſt to be both a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet; With a ſerious warning to the <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> not to uphold and maintain them by a Law, under any pretence whatſoever: As alſo a warning to all People, that (upon peril of their immortal ſouls) they be no longer deluded and bewitched by their Sorceries; But that they come to Chriſt the true Light, which will lead them out of the paths of ſin, into the way of peace.</p>
            <p>By one who (through mercy from the Lord) hath eſcaped the ſnares of ſin and deceit, and bin brought (through Judgement) into His pure fear, known by the Name of <hi>John Chandler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:172526:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172526:2"/>
            <head>A Narrative, plainly ſhowing, that the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> are as truly <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (who got up ſince the daies of the Apoſtles) as the Pope and his Clergy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GIve ear Oh all ye Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> for this word is to you, to ſhew (by the true light which hath enlightned me) that ye are Antichriſt, and that the Spirit of ſpiritual Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Fornication is in and upon you, as truly as in and upon the Pope and his Clergy, ſo called: For ye deny Chriſt the Son of God to be both a King, Prieſt, and Prophet, both by your words and actions; and what doth he or they more? Firſt, Ye deny Chriſt to be a Prieſt, who, by the eternal Spirit, hath offered up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf once for all, to put an end to all carnal Covenants, National Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Miniſtry, and Maintenance, and to perfect for ever them that are ſanctified. Now ye uphold by Doctrine and practiſe the Covenant with the ſeed after the fleſh, as it was with the Jew outward of old; of which, Circumciſion in the fleſh was a ſigne, which were both but fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of the Jew inward, who was to be circumciſed without hands by the circumciſion of Chriſt in putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh: Ye uphold this (I ſay) by ſprinkling of Infants under the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer pretence, which ye apply to them as a Seal of the ſaid Covenant, ſo accounting them as Chriſtians &amp; Members of your Church, which is according to generation, and not according to regeneration, which thing alone gives perſons a right to be Members of Chriſt's Church, which is his body: ſo the matter of your Church is the World, and not the Saints. And as for a National Church: before Chriſt, the true light, was manifeſted in that body which died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there was but one in the whole World, to wit, in the Land of <hi>Judea,</hi> which was a figurative State; to hold forth, that the Saints of Chriſt, in his day, (wherever they were gathered out of the World) were a royal Nation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172526:3"/>and peculiar people unto him, as <hi>Peter</hi> calleth them: &amp; after Chriſt's departure, when the Apoſtles and Saints had received power from on high, they went forth in that power, and by their Miniſtry gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Seed of God out of ſeveral Nations, Cities, and Places, who were the Churches of Chriſt; but ye, in ſtead hereof, have raiſed by your carnal Covenant with the carnal Seed, many National. Churches (as ye call them), and ye neither tremble nor are aſhamed to father them upon Chriſt, who is a pure, holy, and ſpiritual head, and muſt have no other body. But theſe are ſeen in the light to be but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cities of the Nations, which <hi>John</hi> in his Revelation mentioneth, which, he ſaith, fell, when great <hi>Babylon</hi> came into remembrance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to give her the Cup of the Wine of the fierceneſſe of his wrath. As for a Nationall Miniſtry, or Miniſtry ſetled all over the Nation, which are your ſelves, it is ſuitable to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional State, to wit, a certain peculiar Tribe, known by diſtinct Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and appropriating the expoſition and opening of the Scriptures to the people, to themſelves; as the Prieſts, the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> were, and did under the Law, before Chriſt, by God's command; which firſt Prieſt-hood there was a neceſſity of diſanulling (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle), by reaſon of its faultineſſe, imperfection, and unprofitableneſs; wherefore Chriſt (whoſe Father's Law to do, was within his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heart) came and offered up himſelf once for all, and ſo put an end to that firſt Prieſt-hood, which ye moſt wickedly and ungodlily ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hold up, together with its maintenance, Tythes, or the Tenth of the encreaſe, (which ceaſed with the firſt Prieſt-hood) moſt wickedly &amp; unjuſtly forcing the ſame from People by a Law of Man, and puniſhing the refuſers, whereas the Jewiſh Prieſt-hood had it by the Law of God; Neither give or allow ye one penny out of it to the Fatherleſſe, Widow, or Stranger: So that, are ye not rightly called Prieſts? Surely ye need not ſnuff at it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for Miniſters of Chriſt ye can in no wiſe be called who thus, ſo viſibly, withſtand his everlaſting Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. Ye are alſo ſeen to deny the Faith of and on Chriſt the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting High Prieſt, though ye will acknowledge his perſon in words, (for how elſe ſhould ye be Antichriſt and the falſe Prophet?) who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring himſelf once for all into the holy of holies, doth give forth liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vertue to all his Members, who wait in his light, to feel his pure life, whereby they are purged and purified thoroughly from ſin, by the living Faith and Hope which entreth within the Vail, and all your vailes and coverings, and ſo are perfected for ever; for Chriſt's work is perfect and everlaſting: But ye cry out, <hi>Blaſphemy, Blaſphemy,</hi> To
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172526:3"/>ſay that Chriſt thoroughly freeth or purgeth any Man or Woman from Sin, while they live here, but in part onely, ſo denying the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of Chriſt's blood which is his life, which cleanſeth thoſe who ſincerely confeſſe their ſins, from all ſin, ſo making them perfect, as pertaining to the conſcience; which I teſtify none can ever be, while any ſin is ſtanding, which, while ſo, will certainly raiſe up guilt and condemnation there, through God's pure witneſſe ſhewing the evil: wherefore, ſince ye (being out of the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) cannot witneſſe Victory over ſin and tranſgreſſion, ye enter not into the true, ſpiritual, and eternal reſt, prepared for the people of God; but maintain and uphold a natural day, to wit, every firſt day of the week, as for an outward Sabbath or Reſt, which ye are not aſhamed to call the Chriſtian Sabbath or Reſt: Is this day the true Chriſtian's reſt? or have they peace with God all the week, and all their daies, and for ever, ſtanding in his everlaſting Covenant, which is to give them Reſt from their labours and ſore bondage? But the Sabbath day which we ſanctify, not ſpeaking our own words, or thinking our own thoughts on his Holy day, which is one continual day, known to him, and his people that ſtand in obedience, ye Prieſt's know not, and how then ſhould ye declare it to others; but your Sabbath which is a natural day, we ſee to be but your Market-day, wherein ye vent your wares for money and not the true Chriſtian's Reſt. Thus do ye plainly deny (Oh ye Prieſts) Chriſt Jeſus the Son of God, to be the onely High-Prieſt. And that he ſhould be a King to reign alone in righteouſneſſe, ye cannot endure; (yet will ye call Him in your Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, King Jeſus, <hi>Judas</hi> like, giving him a Hail-Maſter:) For whereas the Lord God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, hath ſet this his King upon his holy Hill of <hi>Zion,</hi> in this his day, to rule and govern in the hearts of his People, in righteouſneſſe and peace; ye endeavor what ye can to pull him down out of his Throne, and ſet up the Laws of man in his place: For ye have been endeavouring for divers years, and we well know it is your principle ſtill, to force all people in the Nation (be they never ſo tender conſcienced, or never ſo ſenſible of God's power working in their hearts a loathing of your dead traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and idol and carnal Worſhip, and drawing their minds to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in Spirit and truth) to ſubmit to the ſame, and bow to the King of <hi>Babel's</hi> Image, upon pain of great puniſhment; yea at this day do ye ſo ride the Beaſt or tyrannical Magiſtracy, that ye have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Lawes of theirs againſt the Saints, thereby to conſtrain them (if ye could) to yield to your covetous, proud, and wicked Wills, and reſtrain them from oppoſing or troubling of you in your evil waies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172526:4"/>and deceit; when as the Saints who are the Lambs followers, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by their King (Chriſt the Power of God) to croſs and ſtand li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Witneſſes againſt you in all your falſe, wicked, and deceitful pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, whereby ye ſeek, for honour and profits ſake, to keep His Rule &amp; Authority from riſing in the hearts of men; but He muſt and ſhall Reign, till He hath put all His enemies (within and without) under his feet, and made every one bow to his name, which is his power: turning the Beaſt and falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prophet or Whore that is carryed by him, into the lake of fire: for do ye think that the Lord God is not very jealous for His holy Name, (who will be the onely Law-giver of his People) when as Men-ſhall by Lawes made in their own wills, go about to force them to do that which his pure and holy Law in their hearts, and Word, which is like fire in their bones, contradicteth? Is not this for the Beaſt to make direct War with the Lamb, and is it not ſo in this Nation? but the Lamb, and the Saints by his blood, the word of their teſtimony, and loving not their lives unto death, but pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently ſuffering, ſhall have the Victory; and then, wo be to all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and proud of the Earth, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts; for a great War is begun, neither will the Lamb lay down his two edged ſword procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of his mouth which is his word, but in righteouſneſſe will Judge and make War, ſo long as there is but one Nation throughout the World that withſtandeth his living Truth: and we know him nearer than ſo; that in us he will not ſuffer one high im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agination or evil thought to exalt it ſelf unrevenged. Wherefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of your oppoſition againſt the Lord and his Chriſt, leſt ye be ſlain before his face; and ceaſe to infuſe falſely into the Magiſtrates head, that he is the keeper of both Tables, thereby ſtill to animate him, to make Laws about Religion and the Worſhip of God: For it is a lye every way; for he that can keep both Tables in his own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, loveth the Lord God with all his heart, and his neighbour as himſelf; which I am ſure they do not, for they have divers Idols which their hearts run after, as Pride, Riches, and Honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which draw their hearts from God, neither do they to their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as they would be done by, being hard hearted, implacable, unmerciful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor much leſſe can the Magiſtrate cauſe both Tables to be kept by others: For can he by his outward ſword make men love the Lord God with all their hearts, and their neighbour as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or can he onely reſtrain men from doing outward wrong and violence, and conſtrain them outwardly to do juſtice? which is far from keeping of both Tables of the righteous Law, as the Saints that are turned to the true light which makes manifeſt, right well know,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172526:4"/>Ye deny (Oh ye Prieſts) Chriſt the Son of God to be a Prophet alſo, by ſetting up your own manifold Doctrines, Inventions and Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, inſtead of His pure Teachings; who being the true light that lightens every man that cometh into the World, is given by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, to be a Covenant of light to the Nations: that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of the Nations that believeth in that which makes manifeſt his evil deeds, and cometh ſincerely to the light to have all evil diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, judged down, and deſtroyed; might find and feel the light of life quickening him up to God, and giving him power and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over ſin and tranſgreſſion, whereby (that which letted being taken out of the way) peace and reconciliation with the Lord God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth he might come to witneſſe: Thus is Chriſt the Prophet raiſed up by Gods power, whom every one is to hear, leſt he be cut off; but ye Prieſts not only not believe in this light your ſelves, but give cautions to your people how they receive it, calling it a natural and inſufficient light to lead to God, or ſave the ſoul, that ſo ye may in the room thereof, uſher in the Scriptures (which were but words given forth from the light) as the onely rule and guide: whereby ye get much money by repeating them to the People in a forme or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod; for ye know, as People come to know and follow the true teacher which is the holy anointing, or true light within them; they will be taken off from your dead words and teachings, and ſo will no longer put into your mouths, giving their money for that which is not Bread; for ye are convinced in your own conſciences that ye miniſter not to the People by the pure gift of God, or Spirit's Baptiſm, by which the Apoſtles and Saints of Old miniſtred, who before they would ſtir or open their mouths, waited for the Fathers promiſe, even the Spirit of Truth: And therefore to Salve up the matter, have ye moſt falſly and corruptly diſtinguiſhed between extraordinary and ordinary Miniſters of the Church: the Apoſtles who had propheſie, Miracles, and Revelation, ye ſay, were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters: which gifts ceaſing, ordinary Miniſters God teacheth by, to wit, Paſtors and Teachers, who come to be fitted thereto by ordinary meanes; as Languages, Book-Learning, Study, Induſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh ye blind guides! know ye not that the gift of a Paſtor or Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Chriſt's Church, was the effect of the Baptiſm of the Spirit, as well as the gift of an Apoſtle; Propheſie, Revelation, Miracles, or any other? and dare you to aſſume the name of Paſtors or Teachers, and yet deny the Power whereby ſuch formerly miniſtred, which was the Power from on High? Is not this right-Antichriſt to aſſume the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172526:5"/>Office, and out of the Power and Life whereby it ſhould be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred? Nay, denying any ſuch thing to be now, as Revelation, or the gift of diſcerning of Spirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without which none in the Apoſtles days could be Paſtors or Teachers: So ye deny the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe reaching is in all Ages one and the ſame to His; onely in the Apoſtacy from His Light and Truth, He hath bin withdrawn; but now is come to Teach and to Inſtruct His People again; that with the Light they may ſee, diſcern, and comprehend all falſe Prophets; who for many years have filled the World with decait and errour, and by the ſame Light may ſee Him who is inviſible, and the glory that was with Him before the World was: So ſeeing the true Original of all, which is eternall Power and Wiſdom: Riches, Glory, and Honour everlaſting. And becauſe ye Prieſts and blind guides are ſwerved from the light of Chriſt, which ſhould be the onely Counſellour and Director, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye in your ordinary gifts, (as they are called,) which is but carnal wiſdowe, preſume even to ſit in the Temple of God, as God, to wit, by your ſeveral Synods and Councils, which ye (if ye could) would have according to your own minds: who undertake to ſet forth Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, or Rules, and Directories and Faiths, for the Worſhip of God, and to excommunicate, and receive in; and to judge of Truth and Error; and to uſe the Magiſtrate to enjoyn by puniſhment the obſervance thereof: although Chriſt the true Prophet hath directed his People in a new and living way; whoſe teachings and directions theſe Prieſts either wholly deny, or think inſufficient, or elſe they would never preſume to ſet forth Canons, Directories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the people of God to walk by. Thus are ye diſcovered to be compleat Antichriſt; nor want ye any thing of the Pope and his Clergy, in eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential matters, for all your pretended Reformation, onely in ſome ſuperſtitions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe material, ye differ: If ye ſhall ſay, Ye are wronged, in that the Pope takes on him to forgive ſins, as Chriſt's Vicar, which is a high preſumption, which ye are not guilty of; I ſay, you are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſame thing in your corrupted Judgments, and would ſoon make it appear by practiſe, were ye not by God's providence reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; for the Pope's forgiveneſſe of ſins is no more than a declaration outwardly of what he thinks God doth confirme in heaven, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Office or Chaire, as <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor; and ye in your ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Synods and Presbyteries, appropriate the power of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or binding and looſing, to your ſelves, by vertue (as ye think) of Faith and Office; and wherein lyes the difference betwixt you,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172526:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſave in this, That the Pope's preſumption is Monarchical, or done by one man, and yours (as I may ſay), Ariſtocratical, or done by divers, whom ye count the chief of the Church; and what difference is there between one to be called Chriſt's Vicar, and out of his life; and ye to call yourſelves his Miniſters, Paſtors, and Elders, and be out of it alſo: And as for Merits or Juſtification by works, which ye count a damnable Doctrine among the Papiſts, which ye ſay ye utterly deny: See the ſmal difference betwixt them and you herein; for ye both, looking upon a Chriſt without, after the fleſh, but denying the true light within, they think Chriſt died and ſuffered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to make their works meritorious; &amp; ye ſay, your works are accepted for his death and ſufferings, and Interceſſion's ſake; though neither of you (being not come to true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> light in your ſelvs, which leads to the life, which is the blood, in which all works ſhould be done and performed) can, in truth, ſenſe, and feeling, witneſſe acceptation, one no more than the other; ſo that ye, praying, ſinging and preaching in your Steeple-houſes, faſting, or doing any other work in your own Wills, ye muſt of neceſſity look for an acceptation of them for the deed done, if ye will have any, as well as the Papiſts, ſeeing ye know not a living Chriſt in you, in which they muſt be accepted. As for Images, which the Papiſts worſhip: ye make your ſelves, and ſervices, Images for the people to worſhip: as alſo the Lawes of men, which ye ſay are to be obeyed in the things of God, which is a more myſterious and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Idolatry, becauſe not ſo groſly and plainly appearing, and therefore not ſo eaſily to be avoided: alſo ye call the Steeple-houſe or Tower-houſe, a Church, which is groſs and ſottiſh I dolatry. And whereas perhaps ye will ſay, the Pope ſelleth Pardons and, Indulgences for mony, as he did when <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> fell off from him; Can ye make me believe that the ſame thing (in effect) would not appear among you Prieſts, if your Government were eſtabliſhed, who now make gain the chief Motive of your prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and take mony for ſprinkling Infants, Marriages, Burials, Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Would there not be partiality and reſpect of perſons among you, in admitting people to your communion, and in your proceedings in caſting our and receiving into your Church? Have no ſuch things appeared in <hi>Scotland</hi> among their Presbyteries? or in New-<hi>England</hi> at any time? or among you? Did not the Paſtor or Teacher of <hi>Boſton</hi> in New-<hi>England,</hi> not long ago, when the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (ſo called) would have excommunicated the Keeper of Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel for his moſt cruel and inhumane uſage of one of our friends, (through malice and enmity to the Seed of God) hinder their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172526:6"/>againſt him? and do not malice and enmity proceed from the ſame Root, as Covetouſneſſe, Reſpect of Perſons, and the Love of mony do? Nay, did not the Apoſtate Greek Church, for 1200 years age, call one of their Synods or Councels, to wit, the Councel of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> Robbing, or a Councel of Robbers? and are not all theſe Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods, whether Oeconomical, National, Provincial, Claſſical, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ial, in one and the ſame ground? and have they not proceeded from one &amp; the ſame Root, as others before them have done, &amp; what then can be expected but the ſame fruit?</p>
            <p>Wherefore, Oh ye Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> open your eyes and ſee what a Goſpel-Miniſtry ye do at preſent, and think ye ought to, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as are the Prieſts: and conſider that in ſo doing, ye are but the Beaſt ſpoken of by <hi>John</hi> in his Revelation, which carried the Whore, and ſo are enemies to Chriſt's Kingdome. Know ye aſſvredly, That whilſt ye do this, the hand of the Lord is againſt you, and the Lamb will never ceaſe making War with you by his Saints, his Followers, and that by the Word of his Mouth ye ſhall be ſlain: and if ye will not withdraw your power from ſupporting, and by Laws upholding theſe falſe Prophets, and their Maintenance; (for denying of which, and divers other things, the Saints have greatly ſuffered, and are ſtill lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereunto); that both ye and they ſhall go down into the Pit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it: whoſe anger is hot in this his day, againſt all unrighteouſneſſe of men, wherewith the earth hath been long corrupted and burdened; who hath looked down from heaven in pitty, and at length viſited his captivated Seed, and wo be to the Oppreſſour which in the day of the Lord's delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance would ſtill hold it in the chains of Babyloniſh captivity. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore chuſe you whether ye will now leave a good ſavour behind you, or a ſtink in the noſtrils of God and his People; whether ye will be accounted thoſe that undo every yoak, and let the oppreſſed go free, or Magiſtrates that bear not the Sword in vain, but ſuch as are a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to evill doers, (of whom the Prieſts are the chief) and a praiſe to them that do well: or whether ye will, by the Saints who do and ſhall walk in the light of the Lamb, be eſteemed the Beaſt which puſheth at the Saints and innocent Ones, which (ſaith <hi>John</hi>) opened his mouth in Blaſphemy againſt God to blaſpheme his Name, and his Tabernacle and thoſe that dwell in heaven, miſcalling the truth, calling them Sectaries, Heretiques, Seducers, Enthuſiaſts, Troublers of <hi>Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> Know this Oh thou Parliament! and all future par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, that while the falſe Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this or theſe three Nations, are upheld of you by a Law, or any kind of ſet-maintenance whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172526:6"/>that the Seed and Saints of God muſt needs ſuffer: and if ſo, How can a Bleſſing, and not a Curſe, from the Lord God of heaven and earth, be expected? For this is the Lord's promiſe, to his Church in the laſt daies, The Nation that will not ſerve thee ſhall periſh, yea, (ſaith God) thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly waſted: Wherefore, ſince it's hard for you (though great and lofty) to kick againſt the pricks; and for ye Pot-ſheards of the earth to ſtrive againſt your Maker; and ſince the Lord God Almighty hath decreed the utter ruine of the Whore, that hath bewitched all Nations from his pure life by her Sorceries and Iuchantments, and ſince the Prieſts are ſeen by the light of Chriſt, to be ſuch Sorcerers, and the generality of theſe three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be thus bewitched; I adviſe you in the love of the Lord (O ye of the Parliament, and all other that are called Magiſtrates, to break off your ſins by repentance in your own particulars, to wit, your Pride, Covetouſneſſe, love of Money, the Honour and Glory of this wicked World, reſpect of Perſons, giving and receiving Honour one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Courting one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which hinders you from believing in the true light, which will ſhew you, and reprove you for all theſe things, and more, if ye hearken to it, and in humility and lowlineſs of mind, do ſeek the honour that cometh from God onely; which is his gracious acquittance and acceptance of all the penitent, who turn unto him, with their whole hearts, ſtamping his Image and Mark upon them, &amp; by his eternal Spirit witneſſing in their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that they are his, and ſhall receive an eternal Inheritance as Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires with Chriſt; this is honour enough, and will blaſt all the fading Honour and Glory of the World as a flowr: And Oh ye Magiſtrates &amp; Rulers! till ye come to witneſſe ſomewhat of this in your own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, I cannot expect that ye ſhould act aright and thorowly for God: Now there is a Propheſie in <hi>John</hi>'s Revelation, that the Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their Honour &amp; Glory into the Holy City, new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that comes down from God out of Heaven; As any of you ſhall do ſo, ye will truly and freely give all Honour to the Lord, and expect none but what He giveth you: then would none of you dare to make any Law againſt the Saints or the Truth; but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Or to maintain the falſe Prophet, but would leave him to himſelf, to ſtand upon his own Legs; but into this (O ye Rulers of the Earth) ye are not yet come, but are at preſent ſeeking your own Honour, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and Intereſts, and being out of Gods living Power, run to State-po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, to make that your refuge, and a cover for your preſent actings; ſaying, if we ſhould not maintain and uphold a National Mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tery,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172526:7"/>we ſhould not be like any nation; and the Nation it ſelf would be ſo incenſed and divided, that the deſtruction thereof would be feared; alſo how ſhould ſo many Miniſters with their Families live? Now ye Magiſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and Rulers, conſider in the fear of God, where ye are that thus reaſon: where were the Jews when they forſook and ſtood not in the counſel of the Lord, but would be as other Nations: And ſhall the Antichriſtian State in the ſeveral Nations (think ye) uphold it ſelf alwayes by the Nations taking example by each other, ſo as to prevent the intended purpoſe of the Lord God in the Whore of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> deſtruction? Aſſure your ſelves that this block will not hinder An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts Kingdome in this Nation one moment the longer from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, than the Lord God hath determined. Then, as for the fear of ſo greatly incenſing and dividing the Nation, know ye not, that thoſe who ſtand ſimply and ſingly in the counſel of the Lord faithfully to do his will, ſhall be carried thorow all oppoſition and danger? doth any thing weaken and deject the hearts and ſpirits of men but ſin? I find nothing ſo to do; while the Jews of old, kept out of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt the Lord, the promiſe was, one ſhould chaſe ten, and ten put a thouſand to flight; So ye, if ye knew the will of God, and had ſincere hearts to do it, need not fear what man could do: yea, I affirm A bleſſing ſhould be in your right hand, and upon the Nation, ſo as it ſhould be preſerved in peace and plenty; for this is the Lords promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. that as his way is known upon Earth, and his ſaving health unto all Nations, the People ſhall praiſe the name of the Lord, and be glad and ſing for joy; becauſe the Lord ſhall Judge &amp; Govern he Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Righteouſly upon the Earth; then (ſaith the Spirit) ſhall the Earth yield her increaſe, and God even our own God ſhall bleſſe us; God ſhall bleſs us, and all the ends of the Earth ſhall fear him. And is not this a beggerly and ſlaviſh thing (though bearing the ſhew of charity and pitty) to let the fear of an outward livelyhood, of ſome, to be a hinderance of doing the will of God, who giveth life &amp; breath &amp; all things. Hath not Chriſt ſaid, and do not the Prieſts acknowledge and Preach as much; that men ſhould firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and all other things ſhall be added? Now if the Prieſts State and Kingdom be diſcovered by the light, to be a Kingdom of darkneſſe, for which cauſe they ought not to be upheld and maintained by the Magiſtrate; Let them firſt of all repent and be humble, and come to the Light which leads the way into Gods Kingdom, which ſtands in Peace, Righteouſneſſe, Purity, Holineſſe, and Joy in the Holy Spirit; ſo waiting and ſeeking for this Kingdom, in the light, out of their own Wills and Wiſdoms, and the Lord by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172526:7"/>his providence will ſurely provide for them and theirs: for there is enough in the Creation for every one with contentment. And love is with the Saints, who know allought to be fed and nouriſhed in an honeſt, upright and juſt, but not in an unjuſt way: and therefore can they not pay them (in the way they are in) one ſix pence willingly, though 'twere to the loſſe of all. Beſides, Oh ye Rulers! doth the Lord God ſay any where that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould be a whit the more ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Merchants Wives and Childrens ſakes? What is a worldly Intereſt to the glory of God, and the Salvation of Souls? Wherefore lay ye aſide, I adviſe you, theſe and all ſuch ſlaviſh objections: for they will not juſtifie or excuſe your actings before the Throne of God, or anſwer to that of God in your conſciences, which calleth for Juſtice, Righteouſneſſe, Holineſſe and Equity. And ye people of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conſider, that it is not a leight thing that ye are deceived, deluded, and captivated by the Prieſts and ſalſe Prophets, ſo as to believe lyes: for, ſaith the Apoſtle, the man of ſin ſhould come with all deceive-ableneſſe of unrighteouſneſſe in them that periſh, who becauſe they received not the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God gave them up to ſtrong deluſions to believe lies: that they all might be damned, who believe not the Truth, but have pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe: Mark People, the man of ſin, the Spirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour which worketh in the Myſtery of iniquity, deceiveth with all unrighteouſneſſe, and thoſe who have pleaſure in that unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but love not the truth, are ſuffered to beieve lies that they all may be damned: Oh lamentable! Little do people think what Coals of Indignation they heap upon their own heads, that hate the light that reproveth their evil deeds and deceit, and yet call themſelves Chriſtians, that plead for the Prieſts, the Beaſt, and the Whore, and Idol-worſhips, and ſin as long as they live: hating, reviſing, deriding, and perſecuting the Saints who ſtand as Witneſſes with Chriſt the Light againſt all theſe things. Heate alſo what <hi>John</hi> ſaith <hi>Revelations</hi> 13. (which Book is a Propheſie of theſe times) ſaith he, All that dwell upon the Earth ſhall worſhip the Beaſt, whoſe names are not written in the Book of Life, of the Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World (if any man hath an ear to hear let him hear:) where by he ſheweth) that its a thing of great concernment for people to conſider who they worſhip, fear, obey and ſerve, whether God, or Man, and his Laws and Will, leſt they are for ever excluded from, and never enjoy a part in eternal life. But perhaps, people, ye will ſay, what is it to worſhip the Beaſt or his Image or likeneſſe; For we ſcarce know what thou meaneſt?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:172526:8"/>To worſhip the Beaſt or his Image, is to do whatſoever the falſe Antichriſtian Powers of the Earth ſhall command you to do and obey in the faith and ſervice of God; ſo as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f they command what Religion people ſhould profeſſe, what manner or form of worſhip they ſhall uſe in their Steeple-houſes, what they ſhall do againſt the Saints and Servants of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are ready (like <hi>Iſſachar</hi> who bowed down his back to the burden) to obſerve the ſame, not minding or conſidering what the light of Chriſt in their conſciences tells them, or leads them unto, and whether it be pleaſing or diſpleaſing in the ſight of God; ſo that if the Magiſtrate will have them keep a Faſt, they keep it, or a natural day for a Sabbath, they will obſerve it; or to hear Praying in their Steeple-houſes firſt, then Reading, then ſinging of a Pſalm, then Praying again, then Preaching in the Prieſt's dead form, then Praying again, and then a Bleſſing (ſo called) on the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: they readily do and hear all, and ſo in other things, though out of the life of God in which all Sacrifices ſhould be offered up; and not moved thereto by the Spirit of God. Or if the Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any of them to hale the Saints to priſon, or otherwiſe puniſh them, they will do it, ſaying, In all ſuch things, we are commanded by the higher Powers, and therefore we muſt obey: This, People, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, is to obey Man, rather than God; yea, grievous Idolatry, for the Lord ſaith in every one of you, Thou ſhall have no other Gods but me: now what a man ſerveth and obeyeth, that is his god; ſo the Lord all this while is forgotten, who is the higher Power; and man, an empty &amp; nothing-Creature obey'd, which muſt needs kindle his holy anger againſt all ſuch Idolaters, for he hath ſaid, His glory will He not give to another, nor His praiſe to any graven Image; now, People, that is not onely an Image, which is made of Wood or Stone, but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever created thing any ſets up in his heart to ſerve or obey, beſides, or more than his Creator: Theſe ſayings are true and faithful. Therefore fear and tremble all people before the Mighty God, who made the Heavens and the Earth, and all that is therein; who gives man his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Earth, &amp; time and means to come out of his fallen and curſed eſtate by diſobedience, which meanes, is by his Son Chriſt the ſecond Adam, who is made a quickning Spirit to all that receive Him, who is the true Light that enlighteneth every man that cometh into the World, whereby they may ſee their evil thoughts, words, wayes, &amp; works, and have Power, by believing in the light, to overcome the evil with good, that ſo, the evil being forſaken, and the good cleaved unto, they (by the power &amp; beauty thereof) may be transformed into the pure Image of God, which was loſt by the Fall, whereby the whole Creation
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172526:8"/>hath bin brought out of order: that ſo peace &amp; reconciliation with their Creator, they may come to feel in themſelves, which is a moſt happy and bleſſed condition; for this I bear my Teſtimony unto, before all Nations upon the Earth, that they can never come to enjoy peace with the Living pure Lord God of Life, in whoſe favour is Life; any further than they come out of ſin and tranſgreſſion, and feel their hearts purged and cleanſed from the filth thereof; for the Lord is pure and holy, who can behold no iniquity without reproof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he finds it: So that its but in vain for any one to talk or think of juſtification by a Chriſt without, and not to feel his living vertue, purifying their ſouls by his good ſpirit within them, but denying it there; for none but the pure in heart ever did, or ever ſhall ſee the face of the pure God. Wherefore, ye people of <hi>England,</hi> let not the Prieſts deceive you any longer with their too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>row coverings, and with the pillows they have ſo long ſewed under your arm-holes, for lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, whereby ye have been lulled aſleep in a wicked ſecurity, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your ſelves good Chriſtians if ye have but kept your Church, as ye call it (which to the Peoples underſtanding hath bin no more but a Steeple-houſe, which is like the Papiſts) and had an outward confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Religion, though out of the power of godlineſſe, living in all manner of ſin and licentiouſneſſe; for now is the Lord riſen to awaken the Earth, having put life into his witneſſes again, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but Propheſie, and teſtifie againſt the World, that their deeds are evil, though they ſuffer unto death therefore, as ſome of the Lords ſervants have (within this few years) done: that ſo the Lords purpoſe in raiſing them up, may be accompliſhed; which is to gather his precious ſeed which ſhall inherit the promiſe of life, and to lay the wicked and diſobedient under eternal condemnation; for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of the Kingdom is like a Net caſt into the Sea, which having ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and drawn to ſhoare both the good and the bad, the good are received into Veſſels, and the bad are caſt away: So righteous <hi>Abel</hi> and his offering is accepted, but <hi>Cain,</hi> the wicked one, envious and murderer, is rejected, and is but a Vagabond, though he build a City; for the day of the Lord burns, and ſhall burn as an oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly ſhall be ſtubble: and the day cometh that ſhall burn them up, that it ſhall leave them neither Root nor Branch; but unto thoſe that fear the name of the Lord, ſhall the Sun of Righteouſneſſe ariſe with healing in his wings, and they ſhall go forth and grow up as Calves in the Stall, and they ſhall tread down the wicked, for they ſhall be as aſhes under the ſoles of their feet, as already they appear to be.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
